The Victor D'Amico Papers
The Museum of Modern Art, Publisher
Victor D'Amico Papers
1926-2011 (bulk 1942-1969)
The Museum of Modern Art. Museum Archives 11 West 53 Street New York, NY 10019-5497 Phone: (212) 708-9617 Fax: (212) 408-6385 Email: archives@moma.org
Victor D'Amico; The Museum of Modern Art Department of Education
36.3 linear feet 66 5" manuscript boxes 1 12x17" flat box 3 16x20" flat boxes 2 23x31" flat boxes 1 5x12" card box
Documentation of the founding Director (1937-1969) of MoMA's Department of Education and the Department's programs during his tenure: exhibitions and teaching materials circulated by the New York City High Schools Program, classes at the War Veterans' Art Center and People's Art Center, the Children's Art Carnival at MoMA and overseas, and summer art classes at the Art Barge; D'Amico's extra-MoMA involvement in progressive museum art education, including his articles, speeches, and participation in the National Committee for Art Education; as well as personal writings, correspondence, honors, and awards.
Biographical Note
A chronology of D'Amico's accomplishments, as well as MoMA activities and programs during his tenure that are relevant to information and items in the Victor D'Amico Papers, is included here:
1904 Born May 19, New York City
1920-1922 Attends Cooper Union, studying fine arts, illustration, and costume design
1924-1926 Attends Pratt Institute, studying art education
1926-1930 Attends Teachers College of Columbia University
1926-1948 Head of Art Department, Fieldston School
1932-1942 Graduate student and adjunct faculty member, Teachers College of Columbia University
1934 Member, General Education Board; conducts 1935 national survey for Rockefeller Foundation: "Art in American Schools"
1937 MoMA initiates "Educational Project" as 2-year pilot, with D'Amico hired part-time as Director while also serving as art teacher at Fieldston School
1937-1948 Young People's Gallery instituted; this space later houses Children's Art Carnival
1937-1970 New York City High Schools Program (joint project of the New York City Board of Education and MoMA) distributes educational material to local high schools. Its expansion between 1937 and 1948 is funded by the Whitney Foundation, General Education Board, and the Rockefeller Foundation.
1939 Department of Education formally inaugurated; Young People's Gallery moves into new Museum building
1939-1945 Future MoMA Director William Rubin studies under D'Amico at Fieldston School
1940 Publishes, with Thomas Munro,Visual Arts in General Education
1940 MoMA holds first classes onsite
1941 25 New York City public high schools are receiving 29 circulating exhibitions
1942 March: First Children's Festival of Modern Art held in a tent in the MoMA garden
1942 Publishes Creative Teaching in Art(revised 1953)
1942 MoMA sponsors Committee on Art in American Education and Society, chaired by D'Amico (later Committee of Art Education, then National Committee on Art Education, and Institute for the Study of Art in Education). Its annual conferences are held at MoMA and other venues.
1942-1954 Children's Holiday Art Carnivals held at MoMA
Summer 1944-June 1948 War Veterans' Art Center, sponsored by Mrs. John D. (Abby Aldrich) Rockefeller, Jr., and Trustee Stephen C. Clark, eventually involves 1,485 participants in quarters first on W. 56th Street and then at 681 Fifth Avenue. The space doubles as children's education location, with adjustable-height desks designed by D'Amico.
1947 Publishes, with Julia Hamlin Duncan,How to Make Pottery and Ceramic Sculpture
June 1948 Veteran's Art Center moves to 21 West 53rd Street; renamed People's Art Center
1948 Resigns from Fieldston and is employed full time at MoMA
1949 Publishes, with Charles J. Martin,How to Make Modern Jewelry
1950 First parent/child classes held in People's Art Center
September 1951 People's Art Center moves to 2nd and 3rd floors of Philip-Johnson-designed MoMA office space at 21 West 53rd Street
1951 Publishes, with Kendall T. Basset and Arthur B. Thurman,How to Make Objects of Wood
1952-1953 NBC television program for children and parents "Through the Enchanted Gate" introduces family art activities to a national audience. A printed guide is distributed to families to help them continue the activities at home, and offers the opportunity to submit works of art for display on the program.
1954 Publishes, with Moreen Maser and Frances Wilson,Art for the Family
1955 MoMA first offers summer art classes at Ashawagh Hall, Springs, Long Island, near the D'Amicos' summer home; then on barge Kearsarge in Napeague Harbor, Amagansett
1955 Special study program is inaugurated to explore problems in teaching art and to circulate the findings to teachers and schools through reports, publications, and visual aids
1956 First Summer Vacation Painting Classes for parents and children held on Long Island
1957 Children's Art Carnival commissioned for international trade fairs in Milan and Barcelona
1957 Publishes Art of the Young Child(2nd edition 1960; 3rd revised edition 1968)
1958 Children's Art Carnival featured in U.S. Pavilion of Brussels World's Fair under auspices of U.S Department of Commerce
1960 MoMA's Modern Art Institute formed, assuming responsibility for the Museum's school program
1960 Serves as Chairman, National Committee on Art Education
1960 Publishes Experiments in Creative Art Teaching
1960-1972 MoMA's art teaching center on barge Kearsarge("The Art Barge") is run under the sponsorship of MoMA by The Institute of Modern Art
1961 People's Art Center is operated as an activity of the newly formed Institute of Modern Art, which extends and expands various activities of the Department of Education at MoMA and elsewhere
Winter 1962 Children's Art Carnival donated, at Indira Gandhi's request, to National Children's Museum of India (Delhi) by the Asia Society and the International Council of MoMA; presented by First Lady Jacqueline Kennedy
October 1963 Opens Children's Art Carnival in New Delhi, which also trains Indian teachers in art education
1963-1966 Classes at Art Barge for teachers are taught under auspices of New York University
1964 Philip Johnson designs additional new space for Department of Education programs; People's Art Center (classrooms and gallery space) moves to east wing at 4 West 54th Street
1965 Newly created International Society for Art Education takes over MoMA's leadership role in National Committee for Art Education
1965-1972 Teaches workshops for teachers at New York University
1967 Classes at Art Barge for teachers are taught under auspices of Southampton College
1968 John D. Rockefeller, 3rd, Fund partially underwrites planned Children's Art Caravan, contingent on additional funding
May 1969 MoMA announces changes in its educational services to follow D'Amico's retirement, including expansion of programs for schoolchildren to visit the Museum, teacher training, and schools programs in disadvantaged areas, replacing the previous programs for children and adults
1969 Children's Art Carnival established as teaching center in Harlem, sponsored by MoMA and Harlem School of the Arts: Betty Blayton Taylor, Executive Director
1969 Retires from MoMA
1970 Begins teaching classes for grade school teachers at the Metropolitan Museum of Art
1971 Napeague Institute of Art formed to run Art Barge summer programs; MoMA is landlord of barge until 1982
1973 Children's Art Carnival of Harlem becomes a separate entity
1982 Napeague Institute of Art renamed Victor D'Amico Institute of Art
1987 Dies April 1, in Southampton, New York
Scope and Content
The Victor D'Amico Papers document activities of the founding director of MoMA's Department of Education, and include photographs, correspondence, audio and videotapes, clippings, draft and completed publications, as well as personal documents, awards, and honors. They also provide information on D'Amico's non-MoMA involvement in education, including his professional writings, speeches, and conference presentations, especially related to the National Committee for Art Education. Most of the collection was received by the Museum Archives from Teachers College, to which it had been donated in 1987 by Victor D'Amico's widow Mabel. It also includes materials that had remained at MoMA after his retirement.
The collection is rich in photographic documentation of D'Amico's best-known programs at MoMA: classes and exhibitions of artwork created at the War Veterans' Art Center, People's Art Center, The Art Barge, and Children's Art Carnival (both at MoMA and overseas) in the 1950s and 1960s; and the extensive program of circulating exhibitions distributed through MoMA's New York City High Schools Program from the 1940s into the early 1970s. The range and variety of photographs are evidence of the extensive publicity that introduced and promoted these programs worldwide, helping to promulgate D'Amico's progressive ideal of art education for a range of populations: children, adults, families, veterans, and seniors.
Arrangement
As received from Teachers College in 2011 (see Note on Provenance), the D'Amico Papers were primarily organized by material type: correspondence, photographs, audiovisual items, and published materials were grouped together in storage cartons. Many of the photographs had been removed from their original housing and numbered for other purposes. These materials are now arranged, together with other items that remained at MoMA after D'Amico's retirement, to document projects and programs of the Department of Education initiated while he was Director (Series I-VII); and his professional and personal activities during and after his tenure at MoMA (Series VIII-XI).
The collection is arranged in 11 series:
Series I. Department of Education Administration,1938-1973
Series II. New York City High Schools Program,[1940s]-1974
Subseries II.A. General Background,[1940s]-1971
Subseries II.B. Alphabetical List of Exhibitions and Slide Programs Distributed to Schools,1941-1974
Series III. Art Education at MoMA,1920s-1982 (bulk 1944-1968)
Subseries III.A. War Veterans' Art Center,1944-1949
Subseries III.B. Slide Talks,1943-1960s
Subseries III.C. Art Classes General,1920s-1982 (bulk 1941-1970)
Series IV. Children's Art Carnival and Caravan,1940s-1979 (bulk 1942-1965)
Subseries IV.A. Children's Art Carnival,1940s-1979 (bulk 1942-1965)
Subseries IV.A.i. MoMA and General,1942-1979
Subseries IV.A.ii. Milan,1956-1957
Subseries IV.A.iii. Barcelona,1957
Subseries IV.A.iv. Brussels,1958-1959
Subseries IV.A.v. Harlem,1960-1978
Subseries IV.A.vi. India,1960s-1964, 1969
Subseries IV.A.vii. Multiple Locations,1940s-1960s
Subseries IV.B. "Through the Enchanted Gate,"1952-[1953]
Subseries IV.C. Children's Art Caravan,1960s-1974
Series V. Art Barge,1950s-2011 (bulk 1955-1980s)
Series VI. Exhibitions,1938-1969
Series VII. MoMA Publications,1941-1972
Series VIII. Professional Involvement,1935-1980, 1985, 1996 (bulk 1948-1968)
Subseries VIII.A. Education General,1935-1980, 1985, 1996
Subseries VIII.B. Education-Related Correspondence,1947-1969
Subseries VIII.C. National Committee on Art Education,1943-1969
Series IX. Speeches and Writings,1926-1982 (bulk 1938-1970)
Series X. Personal,1945-1985, 1987, 2003
Subseries X.A. Personal Records and Correspondence,1945-1946, 1951-1985, 2003
Subseries X.B. Awards and Honors,1951-1953, 1964-1981, 1987
Series XI. Printed Materials,1936-1995
Related Material at MoMA and Elsewhere
Within the MoMA Archives, the Public Information Records include extensive clippings regarding nearly every Museum exhibition, personality, and event.
For complementary exhibition-related materials, please consult the Museum's Exhibition Files.
Similarly, the Department of Circulating Exhibitions (C/E) Records include information regarding MoMA exhibitions that toured domestically, and the International Program Records include documentation regarding its International Circulating Exhibitions (ICE).
The Early Museum History: Administrative Records include documentation of early Department of Education activities, including "Through the Enchanted Gate."
Images of exhibitions and various programs, including the Children's Art Carnival, are located in the Photographic Archive. Many of these have been digitized and are available for viewing on MAID, the Museum Archives Image Database, in the MoMA Archives reading rooms.
Teachers College of Columbia University holds the papers of Lois Lord, who taught in the Department of Education at MoMA during D'Amico's tenure and was active in the National Committee on Art Education.
The University Archives of the University of Miami (Ohio) holds records of D'Amico in its Fine Arts/Art Education Archives.
D'Amico, Victor, 1904-1987--Archives.; Children's Art Caravan--Archives.; Children's Art Carnival--Archives.; International Textbook Company--Archives.; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.). Children's festival of modern art. 1942--Archives.; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.)--Congresses--Archives.; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.). Dept. of Education--Archives.; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.). Educational Program. New York City Public School Program--Archives.; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.)--Employees--Archives.; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.)--Exhibitions--Archives.; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.). People's Art Center--Archives.; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.). War Veterans' Art Center--Archives.; National Committee on Art Education (U.S.)--Archives.; Art--Study and teaching (Elementary)--New York (State)--New York--History--Sources.; Art--Study and teaching (Secondary)--New York (State)--New York--History--Sources.; Art--Study and teaching--United States--History--Sources.; Art museums--Educational aspects--History--Sources.; Assemblage (Art)--Sources.; Child artists--History--Sources.; Architectural plans; Audiocassettes; Black-and-white slides; Books; Catalogs; Clippings (information artifacts); Color slides; Correspondence; Degrees (academic); Drawings (visual works); Manuscripts (document genre); Photocopies; Photographic prints; Tear-sheets; Transcripts; Videocassettes
Restrictions on Access
The records are open for research and contain few restricted materials.
Provenance
The bulk of the Victor D'Amico Papers were received by the Museum Archives in 2011 from Columbia University Teachers' College, to which they had been donated by Mabel D'Amico after her husband's death in 1987. Beginning in 2007, MoMA, together with The Art Barge and Teachers' College, entered into a series of discussions regarding the Papers' ultimate location. The MoMA Archives was determined to be their logical location, due to the extensive documentation of Museum program activities contained within the Papers. Five boxes of materials were received from former MoMA art teacher Arlette Buchman in January 2012. That year, various materials stored at MoMA by the Department of Education and Photographic Archive were determined to have been previously separated from the D'Amico records and were included for processing with the Victor D'Amico Papers.
Additional Descriptive Data
Explanation of Abbreviations
MoMA is The Museum of Modern Art.
ALS is an Autograph Letter Signed.
TLS is a Typed Letter Signed.
re: stands for regarding.
Container List
- Series I. Department of Education Administration, 1938-1973
  The series includes a small amount of administrative material from the Department of Education during D'Amico's tenure. Notable are three folders (I.14-16) of correspondence and other information about the reconfiguration of the Department at D'Amico's retirement, and the discontinuation of onsite art classes at the Museum. Course descriptions and registration forms are included in Series III.C. Art Classes General.
  Historical Note
  D'Amico's first involvement at MoMA was as head of the Museum's Educational Project, a two-year pilot project (1937-1939) that was an outcome of the report on art education in museums funded by the Rockefeller Brothers Fund (see also Series VIII. Professional Involvement). The Department of Education was formally inaugurated in 1939; its services to high schools were termed The New York City High Schools Program (see Series II).
  - Evaluation reports, Undated; Blank forms to be filled in by teachers re: students and classes (Box 1, Folder I.1)
  - Reports to Mr. Barr on the Educational Project, 1938-1939, 1940-1941; Includes list of activities and schools participating; minutes of the first Advisory Committee meeting (2/16/1939); Tentative Plans for the Three Year Experiment of the Educational Project with Secondary Schools (6/13/1939) (Box 1, Folder I.2)
  - Advisory Committee Preliminary Report, Spring 1941 (Box 1, Folder I.3)
  - Plans for the Educational Program, 1943-1944; Proposed program of courses for teachers and children (Box 1, Folder I.4)
  - Photographs of D'Amico, [1950s]; B/w prints, some mounted; transparencies (Box 68, Folder I.5*)
  - Sample registration cards; blank folders from People’s Art Center, [1950s] (Box 1, Folder I.6)
  - Memo on staffing, suggested reading, evaluation form, letterhead, 1955, 1969, undated (Box 1, Folder I.7)
  - Letters to and from D'Amico, including personal and work-related, both during and after his tenure at MoMA, 1956-1980; Includes letters (decorated with sketches) from D'Amico to "Kearsargists" while in India and Rome with the Children's Art Carnival [1963], and his "open letter to class on the last day" (1956) (Box 1, Folder I.8)
  - Plans for new art center, and some furnishings for it, 1962; Glass-mounted slides (Box 1, Folder I.9)
  - Presentations at opening dinner, Third Floor Galleries, October 2, 1962; 7" audio reel: Participants included Museum Trustee William A.M. Burden, Museum Director René d'Harnoncourt, Gov. Nelson A. Rockefeller, Gardner Cowles on occasion of The Museum of Modern Art Builds: Models and Photographs of Proposed Building Plans of Museum[MoMA Exh. #710a, October 1, 1962 - cont.].; NOTE: this recording in digital format (Sound Recordings of Museum-Related Events, 62.2, 62.2D) can be used in the MoMA Archives Manhattan reading room (Box 1, Folder I.10)
  - Student aid and scholarship fund, 1963-1968; Receipts for donations, fund-raising letters, account balances and expenses (Box 1, Folder I.11)
  - Supply list, correspondence, teacher material, 1964-1966 (Box 1, Folder I.12)
  - Proposal to Channel 13/WNDT, 1966; For four-program pilot to teach creative art to underprivileged children and their families. Includes correspondence, budget (Box 1, Folder I.13)
  - Correspondence, bills for supplies, memos on future of People's Art Center, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder I.14)
  - Correspondence re: Art Center closing and discontinuation of MoMA art classes, 1969-1970; Includes memo D'Amico-MoMA Trustee Henry Allen Moe (1/28/1969) summarizing accomplishments at MoMA; TLS D'Amico-MoMA Director Bates Lowry (4/10/1969) re: request to postpone planned closing of Art Center; letters from parents and others to MoMA; originals and copies of correspondence sent to MoMA Director and Trustees (Box 1, Folder I.15)
  - Reactions to closing, 1969-1970; Includes original and photocopied letters to MoMA, and responses (Box 1, Folder I.16)
  - Slide orders, 1969; Correspondence re: orders and budgets (Box 1, Folder I.17)
  - D'Amico honored by Governor Rockefeller at Pocantico dinner, [1969]; Draft press release (Box 1, Folder I.18)
  - International Council, 1970-1973; Includes agendas for program committee meetings, schedules of exhibitions, clippings (Box [ENTER], Folder I.19)
- Series II. New York City High Schools Program, [1940s]-1974
  The series includes information on circulating exhibitions, teaching portfolios, slide sets, and other educational materials and their use in programs provided to the New York City public high schools by MoMA's Department of Education during and after D'Amico's tenure.
  MoMA's New York City Public High Schools Program was formally inaugurated in 1937, as one of MoMA's newly formed Education Project's first initiatives. In cooperation with the New York City Board of Education (which, at that time, employed no art teachers), the Program provided circulating exhibitions and teaching materials (including slides, slide talks, teaching portfolios and models, and libraries of reproductions) to schools. It also held programs at the Museum that included opportunities for students to curate exhibitions (see Series VI. MoMA Exhibitions). At the Program's peak in 1957-1958, 59 schools were being provided with more than 100 circulating items.
  Arrangement
  The series is organized into two subseries:
  Subseries II.A. General Background,[1940s]-1971
  Subseries II.B. Alphabetical List of Exhibitions and Slide Programs Distributed to Schools,1941-1974
  - Subseries II.A. General Background, [1940s]-1971
    Scope and Content
    The subseries includes administrative information on the Program, as well as photographic documentation of teaching materials and some exhibitions. No explanations are provided for the abbreviations E.P. and V.P. in the records, but they appear to relate to exhibition and visual materials, respectively.
    - The City, Undated; 12" film reel; Note: This 12" film reel has been transferred to the Museum's Film Study Center, which has the proper facilities for storing and screening it. Researchers should contact the Study Center for further information. Access may be denied due to the film's physical condition. (Box 2, Folder II.A.1)
    - Unidentified Super 8 film reel, Undated; Super 8 film reel; Note: This Super 8 film reel has been transferred to the Museum's Film Study Center, which has the proper facilities for storing and screening it. Researchers should contact the Study Center for further information. Access may be denied due to the film's physical condition. (Box 2, Folder II.A.2)
    - Works of Calder "A", Undated; 11" film reel; Note: This 11" film reel has been transferred to the Museum's Film Study Center, which has the proper facilities for storing and screening it. Researchers should contact the Study Center for further information. Access may be denied due to the film's physical condition. (Box 2, Folder II.A.3)
    - Slide talk: What is Modern Painting?, [1940s]; E.P.1: text to accompany slides (Box 2, Folder II.A.4)
    - Slide talk: What is Modern Sculpture?, [1940s]; E.P. 2A: text to accompany slides (Box 2, Folder II.A.5)
    - Various exhibitions, [1940s-1960s]; Includes photographs of installation at Fieldston school, art teacher, and unidentified images: b/w prints (Box 2, Folder II.A.6)
    - Modern Masters from European and American Collections[MoMA Exh. #97, January 26-March 24, 1940], Questionnaire responses received from high schools. Most are aggregated from individual responses. (Box 2, Folder II.A.7)
    - Look at Your Neighborhood[MoMA Exh. #256, March 29-June 25, 1944], Photographs of panels, box for traveling version of the exhibition: b/w prints mounted on pages previously removed from album (Box 2, Folder II.A.8)
    - Displays on art services for the New York City public schools: Board of Education headquarters, Brooklyn, NY, [October 1945]; Mounted b/w prints removed from post album (Box 2, Folder II.A.9)
    - Mailings to high schools (1 of 7), 1945-1948; Includes list of exhibitions, information on school art departments, form letters (Box 2, Folder II.A.10)
    - Mailings to high schools (2 of 7), 1949-1953; Includes list of exhibitions, information on school art departments, form letters (Box 2, Folder II.A.11)
    - Mailings to high schools (3 of 7), 1954-1958; Includes list of exhibitions, information on school art departments (Box 2, Folder II.A.12)
    - Mailings to high schools (4 of 7), 1959-1963; Includes list of exhibitions, information on school art departments, form letters (Box 2, Folder II.A.13)